welcome to another super Lofa edition of
deep code today what I want to do is
talk about a concept that I've mentioned
a few times in my writing but I don't
believe I've mentioned in the videos and
that is supernormal stimuli and a new
idea that I have come up with in how we
might actually be able to respond to
them
so first what is the super normal
stimulus to get to the bottom of this
idea I think we just have to take a look
at two different things that seem to
show up in our being in the world is
evolved organisms the first is that the
world is big it's complex it contains
all kinds of stuff that we can't post's
possibly hope to fully track and we're
relatively limited so it ends up
happening is that we have to use some
simple model some subset of heuristics
and signs and signifiers and rules of
thumb to make sense of what's going on
in our environment and guide us to make
what we hope are good choices so I'm
gonna call these things the things we
want so we have a set of symbols of
stimuli that we perceive in our
environment and of those we're going to
select a few I'm going to identify those
as being attractive or good and we will
seek them out we'll be willing to take
risks in order to engage with them and
then on the other side we actually have
the actual effects of the choices that
we make in our adaptive fitness in our
environment so if for example we seek
out a shiny red apple looking object and
we consume it and it's poisonous and we
die then you know we've received sort of
the ultimate feedback from our
environment is a bad choice so by
contrast if we seek it out and eat it
and it's full of calories and nutrition
as a consequence we survive more
effectively than those organisms around
us that don't do that then we will get
what I'm going to call what we need so
I'm making instinct and what we want to
what we need what we want is the set of
relatively simple symbols that indicate
what we think are in fact and in fact
are proxies for what we think we need
and what we need is in fact the actual
complex reality that is adaptive to
our environment so this is the first
part there's a separation what we want
and what we need then the second part is
that any given species will have been
involvement with in some particular
actual niche which is going to contain
some distribution of phenomena so it
will have what is in fact normal so if
you say spend all of your time in the
desert your organs involve to the desert
then certain ranges of moisture and
certain ranges of temperature are normal
and as a consequence they're going to be
different phenomenon that are not
normally present in your environment as
a certain intensities or certain
characteristics and these are going to
be other than normal it said that's more
that's it which is it evolution evolved
us to be fit but only within the
constraints of the selection pressures
and so if we find ourselves encountering
something that is well outside of or
different to the selection pressures to
which we are adapted we will not be
adapted to it evolution isn't to sort of
make up lots of redundancy it's really
rather sloppy when it comes to it just
just enough there's kind of a rule of
thumb so so these two pieces combined
then give rise to the problem and the
possibility of supernormal stimuli so
and so then you think about that what it
makes the stimulus super normal is that
again two distinctions well one is that
it takes the the aspects of phenomena
that we are in fact sensitive to the
aspects that are that we want say the
shiny red apple nosov an apple and it
abstracts and distills that into a
concentrated intensity but
simultaneously it is not necessarily and
therefore for it accordingly is not
present to and connected to the
complexity of the phenomenon that was in
fact made it what made it needful or why
we actually were seeking it out
adaptively in the first place so you
might imagine for example a fake apple
it's a very red very shiny very apple it
has no blemishes it looks like the
perfect apple and if you
would have put a child who'd never
encountered such Tintin up to a table
where I had a real Apple and I had a
sort of a superb normal fake apple the
child might actually select the fake
Apple in spite of the fact that it
doesn't you can't eat it as no nutrition
in it and these experiment experiments
have in fact been done famously for
example with a certain species of bird
that sort of dispensed with a lot of the
nonsense of what it means for a mother
bird to encounter a baby bird and
evolution notice that as long as the
mother bird is feeding patches of you
know red that are sort of vaguely
circular shaped at a certain height and
distance then that turns out to be
enough so the mothers want capacity is
oriented towards patches of red it's
need fulness of course is to actually
feed its offspring but that separation
is real and so the mother only really
identifies its heuristic is patches of
red of a certain intensity in color and
if an enterprising and of course this
sort of thing is works in the nest right
we rarely if ever is that ever going to
encounter a patch of red of a certain
size and location in nature but if an
enterprising young scientist comes along
in plants little sticks with patches of
red that are more red and more of the
right shape than the big birds then the
mother will in fact actually try to feed
the the fake maybe bird to the detriment
of its own offspring all right so this
is the this is the point we are even we
humans are relatively helpless when it
comes to these deeply evolved mechanisms
for trying to connect what we want to
what we need and then of course the the
real problem that we're encountering
somewhere massively now is that we
humans have become extraordinarily
capable of giving ourselves what we want
but haven't actually yet reached
anywhere near the same capability of
being able to ensure a binding in actual
lived reality between what we want and
what we need so junk food for example
cotton candy here's something where
we've been able to extract the essence
of sweetness which would attach to the
context of an apple is associated with
something that is in fact good for a
primate
in the forest but we've abstracted it
from that context we've intensified it
in the form of say cotton candy or
skittles and we've completely eliminated
the nutritional content that made it
needful in the first place
and in point of fact actually in a
market environment where you're actually
playing precisely with the limits of a
human beings capacity to make sense of
the binding between what they want and
what they need meaning if you give
people if you spend the energy you spend
the money and effort to give people what
they need even if they have no capacity
to actually know it because they don't
want it you know what they knew that but
they don't want you're very unlikely to
be rewarded in the market place and of
course you'll probably be punished if as
a consequence for your product costs
more so of course the market players
will tend to select for and increasing
skillfulness and being able to identify
isolate and produce supernormal stimuli
to produce wants that are increasingly
abstracted and separate from needs and
and I don't really have to put this in
the lap of modern humanity huge portions
of what makes up culture are supernormal
stimuli and music all forms of
storytelling you know all forms of
fashion and dress and makeup I mean
frankly many of our vocal inflections
are themselves supernormal stimuli
because we have this capacity to
identify what other people want and what
we want and to generate that in the
world but connecting beyond that leap it
leap in the gap to wants and needs is so
far proven to be very difficult didn't
they just I'll just do story time very
quickly so you know the heuristic the
the underlying evolved attraction to say
for example gossip makes sense because
in a human society the well-being of the
tribus is crucial right if I if I as an
individual utterly dependent on the
well-being of my tribe of a tribe begins
to break apart in some way I'm in deep
trouble right so it's important for me
to always be ever so slightly tuned to
how well the tribe is doing and it's
therefore attractive like I will in fact
be paying attention when there's some
sense there's some signal being passed
the
there's some kind of breakdown so I can
make sense of it and respond to it but
of course the the actual reality of
human relationships is relatively spare
right I have had a few quite significant
intense experiences in my life
few of any are ever going to reach the
level that maybe I see in a movie or
read about in a book and they certainly
don't occur with the cominis that is
available when you turn on the TV and
just slip through the channels and so as
a consequence we have this evolved
capacity to be sensitive to drama and to
enter gossip but we have a learned
ability to produce that output in orders
of magnitude in terms both intensity and
in regularity then is part of our
natural environment and so of course we
now live in a world we're gonna read
People magazine and people go and watch
you know Avengers age of Ultron these
are just a different way of packaging
the notion of supernormal stimuli and I
hope you know the key thing here at this
level is to recognize that left to its
own devices this is disastrous that
there's a massive breakdown in adaptive
capacity when we get what we want
without regard to what we need it's a
huge Jam I mean it's effectively the
same thing as taking heroin instead of
actually being successful in life or
spending all day long and clicking on
your phone instead of making good
decisions right you're you're you're
we're addicted we all addictions at the
end of the day are addictions to certain
neurotransmitters and supernormal
stimuli are different phenomenal
mechanisms for allowing us to be fully
addicted to certain neurotransmitters
without regard at all or at least
without much regard to the degree to
which those are actually giving us good
signs that we're making good choices in
in our lives and you know in the
contemporary social environment the
culture that we live in now supernormal
stimuli are supersaturated in this is
breaking down our individual collective
capacity so how might we respond to that
and here's where I have something which
is very much conjecture but I think it's
very interesting because I suspect we
may have actually figured this out we
just have lost a thread I would like to
propose for your consideration
the concept of the sacred and the
various other things that are associated
with the sacred like awe and reverence
and humility are actually precisely the
right response to supernormal stimuli in
fact may have been fact been developed
among humans for that reason so if we
think for example of alcohol and you
notice that in many traditions alcohol
is is obligated to be bound to some kind
of sacred context and so on some
periodic basis we get together we drink
wine we get drunk and when we're outside
of that context it is absolutely
prohibited this may actually be an
awesome way to make use of the fact of
supernormal stimuli on one hand the
ability to do a religious or a profane
prohibition of something really
effectively police's what otherwise
might be a very difficult thing to avoid
it uses social system feedback to help
people make the choice not to get
addicted to something and but then on
the other hand the release valve of
having access to that in a context which
is designed if it's well designed to
reinforce meaningful things you know so
if we have this sacred ritual where we
consume alcohol and it connects to
things like creativity conviviality
connection to that which is greater than
ourselves liminal States various ways of
opening up and shifting and shaping
relationships if you could create that
sacred container and then in that
container invests it with the
attractiveness of supernormal stimuli
and then anything other positive aspects
that happen to open up what supernormal
this particular set of supernormal
stimuli power alright you've actually
invented a very powerful tool for
shifting a lot of the negative potential
of supernormal into it may be a very
powerful binding energy that is deeply
needful for the human beings they're
using it and so so maybe that's exactly
right you can think about Oh for example
that ah is what happens when we
encounter something which is super
normal to our ordinary perception so I
said when you encounter something like
the Grand Canyon this is massively more
tense and experience then is part of the
hominin devolved environment in most
people's developmental environment so
you enter into it and the part of you
that is designed to evaluate the quality
of an environment for say its fitness
for habitation is just inadequate to
process this grandeur and so pow you're
hit you're super normally overloaded and
you feel the sense of awe but we have a
notion of a relationship a right
relationship to to awe a notion for
example the the word awful that one
should be very careful in relationship
to awe you know a notion of humility
that perhaps one should have is as a
reverence and relationship to those
things that have this characteristic and
so perhaps the toolkit already was
developed that early humans already were
running up against the problem
supernormal stimuli and they developed
an entire set of practices that were
adapted to this problem and were able to
reposition it in the direction of being
adapted for the individuals and the
societies so then if that's true and the
question would then be can we use it is
that it took at the we can make use of
can we can we moderns rein in our insane
and reckless proliferation supernormal
stimuli in all directions and we harness
that energy that capacity in that
potential in positive directions by
making use of this toolkit of the sacred
can we for example take our storytelling
capability and recognize that the
stories that we tell are by definition
sacred and and treat them as such can we
imagine treating something else say but
in all as the Star Wars trilogy as a
sacred text and recognized that the the
prequels were in fact a profane
violation of that sacredness I think all
of us intuitively sense that the second
third Matrix movies were a certain kind
of deep profanity and a violation which
is not to say by the way that things
like transformers were the highest form
of the sacred to be sure they're already
participating in a significant level of
profanity
but nonetheless we can start somewhere
and begin the process is just taking
that stance and this is very interesting
we don't do this now we've we've very
much thrown out the baby with the
bathwater
with regard to the sacred and it may
even seem cynically obviously foolish
maybe infantile or stupid to imagine the
notion of a an artist a creator not
being able to ruthlessly exploit through
all available commercial merchandising
means the object of their creation their
stories and yet perhaps that is
precisely the antidote and by the way
I'm not piling on storytellers I just
happened to watch the movie ready player
one recently so it's ready to mind but
the same thing goes for everyone else on
the planet who is in the process right
now of creating some kind of supernormal
stimuli that we may in fact find
ourselves in a contemporary environment
of having to recognize the need fulness
of perceiving the sacred everywhere and
therefore becoming very good at things
like awe and reverence and humility
well perhaps worth consideration